<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>docker on Mike&#39;s Dev / Data Science Blog</title>
    <link>http://mikewright.me/tags/docker/</link>
    <description>Recent content in docker on Mike&#39;s Dev / Data Science Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="http://mikewright.me/tags/docker/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Docker</title>
      <link>http://mikewright.me/blog/original/2015-02-06-docker/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://mikewright.me/blog/original/2015-02-06-docker/</guid>
      <description>I love Docker and I really enjoy developing on a stable nix-like environment. But with the current limitation of the docker daemon requiring the linux kernel to work, I am left trying to create the best experience that I can while developing on a mac.
Why not just use boot2docker So docker does provide a solution for most people which is called boot2docker. This solution provides the native docker client for mac, virtualbox and a minimum linux os for virtualbox that you can use as the docker daemon.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Docker and Continuous Delivery</title>
      <link>http://mikewright.me/blog/original/2015-02-06-docker-and-continuous-delivery/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://mikewright.me/blog/original/2015-02-06-docker-and-continuous-delivery/</guid>
      <description>I am a huge fan of continuous delivery, of release code as soon at it is written and passes the automated test gates. I am also a fan of having a deployment system that can be more closely managed by me (the engineer). Using docker at work we have been able to create a system that allows us to define a running container and using gates, continuously deploy this simple container to many different environments (stage, prod, etc).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>EC2 Container Service</title>
      <link>http://mikewright.me/blog/original/2014-12-01-ec2-container-service/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://mikewright.me/blog/original/2014-12-01-ec2-container-service/</guid>
      <description>At AWS re:Invent (November 2014) a new technology was introduced. This was the AWS EC2 Container Service. A service provided by AWS to run docker containers on top of EC2 instances.
We have been using docker for a while now within our organization, and I have to say that I am a huge fan of Docker. This is a great step in the right direction and I believe can help to decrease deploys to AWS while increasing stability and extensibility of a given architecture.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
